<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org">
<title>An simple R interface to Google Documents</title>
<para>
This illustrates how to use the code that we put together 
quite rapidly to communicate with the  Google Documents
manager.  It uses the XML and RCurl packages and illustrates
that it is relatively quick and easy to use their primitives to interact
with Web services.
</para>
<para>
The first thing to do is login using <r:func>getGoogleAuth</r:func>.
You specify your login name for Google, e.g. dtemplelang@gmail.com,
and your password for that account.
<r:code>
auth = getGoogleAuth("dtemplelang@gmail.com", getOption('GoogleDocsPassword'))
</r:code>
We can put this "permanently" into a Curl handle so that we don't
need to specify it in all the calls with
<r:code>
con = getGoogleDocsConnection(auth)
</r:code>
We now just pass <r:var>con</r:var> as the value for the
<r:arg>curl</r:arg> parameter in calls to the other functions.
In the future, we might provide an interface that avoids this such
as
<r:code eval="false">
 con$getDocs()
 names(con)
</r:code>
and where the <r:var>con</r:var> value is implicitly provided.
</para>
<note>
<para>
We do have to specify auth when calling <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func>.
</para>
</note>
<para>
Having logged in, we can find out about the existing documents.
<r:code>
docs = getDocs(con)
</r:code>
This is a list of R descriptions from the XML contents.
<r:code>
names(docs)
<r:output>
[1] "my foo1"                                         
[2] "my foo1"                                         
[3] "my foo1"                                         
[4] "my foo"                                          
[5] "another bob"                                     
[6] "\"~/foo.csv\""                                   
[7] "SampleDoc"                                       
[8] "Copy of This is a sample document that we are..."
[9] "bob"                                             
</r:output>
</r:code>
<r:code>
names(docs[[1]])
<r:output>
 [1] "id"         "published"  "updated"    "category"   "title"     
 [6] "content"    "alternate"  "self"       "edit"       "edit-media"
[11] "author"     "feedLink"  
</r:output>
</r:code>
<r:code>
docs[[1]]
<r:output><![CDATA[
$id
[1] "http://docs.google.com/feeds/documents/private/full/document%3Adfwhmfk3_6c26hc6gr"

$published
[1] "2008-09-24 14:02:56 PDT"

$updated
[1] "2008-09-24 14:02:56 PDT"

$category
                                        scheme 
       "http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#kind" 
                                          term 
"http://schemas.google.com/docs/2007#document" 
                                         label 
                                    "document" 

$title
[1] "my foo1"

$content
                                                                                                                                                 type 
                                                                                                                                          "text/html" 
                                                                                                                                                  src 
"http://docs.google.com/feeds/download/documents/RawDocContents?action=fetch&justBody=false&revision=_latest&editMode=false&docID=dfwhmfk3_6c26hc6gr" 

$alternate
                                               rel 
                                       "alternate" 
                                              type 
                                       "text/html" 
                                              href 
"http://docs.google.com/Doc?id=dfwhmfk3_6c26hc6gr" 

$self
                                                                                rel 
                                                                             "self" 
                                                                               type 
                                                             "application/atom+xml" 
                                                                               href 
"http://docs.google.com/feeds/documents/private/full/document%3Adfwhmfk3_6c26hc6gr" 

$edit
                                                                                         rel 
                                                                                      "edit" 
                                                                                        type 
                                                                      "application/atom+xml" 
                                                                                        href 
"http://docs.google.com/feeds/documents/private/full/document%3Adfwhmfk3_6c26hc6gr/fli10bmo" 

$`edit-media`
                                                                                     rel 
                                                                            "edit-media" 
                                                                                    type 
                                                                             "text/html" 
                                                                                    href 
"http://docs.google.com/feeds/media/private/full/document%3Adfwhmfk3_6c26hc6gr/fli10bmo" 

$author
dtemplelang@gmail.com 
        "dtemplelang" 

$feedLink
                                                                          rel 
                       "http://schemas.google.com/acl/2007#accessControlList" 
                                                                         href 
"http://docs.google.com/feeds/acl/private/full/document%3Adfwhmfk3_6c26hc6gr" 

attr(,"class")
[1] "GoogleDocument"
]]></r:output>
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
We can turn these into a data frame with
<r:code>
as(docs, "data.frame")
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
We can fetch a document with 
<r:code>
getDocContent(docs[["SampleDoc"]], con)
</r:code>
or directly by the name of the document
<r:code>
getDocContent("SampleDoc", con)
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
We can remove a document with
<r:code>
deleteDoc("my foo1", con)
</r:code>
or
<r:code>
deleteDoc(docs[[1]], con)
</r:code>
You can check what files remain with
<r:code>
names(getDocs(con))
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
Finally, to upload a file from your system to your Google Documents account, 
we use <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func>.
For this function, you currently have specify a value for the <r:arg>auth</r:arg>
parameter. This is the value returned by <r:func>getGoogleAuth</r:func> earlier
on.
</para>
<para>
<r:func>uploadDoc</r:func> you can supply a file name or the actual
content to upload.
If the value of <r:arg>content</r:arg> matches a file name,
then we read the contents of that  file and upload that string.
If this is a binary file, you should read the contents yourself
and pass those as the value for <r:arg>content</r:arg>.
</para>
<para>
We try to determine the type of document (e.g. a spreadsheet, a Word
document, a CSV file) from the extension of the filename (using
<r:func>findType</r:func> and matching the extension - MIME type table
from Google's documentation).  If the extension doesn't match or if
you are specifying the content directly, you should specify a vale for
the <r:arg>type</r:arg> parameter.  This can either be the MIME type
(or an initial part thereof), e.g "text/html" or "text/tab", or you
can provide the corresponding extension, e.g. "htm" or "tab".
</para>
<para>
The <r:arg>name</r:arg> parameter allows you to specify a name to be
used as the title of the document in the Google Documents manager panel.
</para>
<para>
Note that Google cannot convert all types of documents and
does not necessarily even handle "rich" CSV files.
</para>
<para>
So let's upload a CSV file with the contents
<programlisting>
1, 2, 3
4, 5, 6
</programlisting>
We'll first upload the contents directly
<r:code>
x = "1, 2, 3\n4, 5, 6\n"
uploadDoc(x, auth, name = "direct csv", type = "csv")
</r:code>
If we put the contents in the file /tmp/foo.csv,
then we can upload this as 
<r:code>
uploadDoc("/tmp/foo.csv", auth)
</r:code>
Here <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func> can infer the MIME type and the 
name from the local file name.
</para>
<para>
Binary files are slightly more complex.
<r:code>
f = system.file("sampleDocs", "SampleDoc.doc", package = "RGoogleDocs")
uploadDoc(f, auth, type = "doc", binary = TRUE)
</r:code>
To upload a spreadsheet
<r:code>
f = system.file("sampleDocs", "SampleSpreadsheet.xls", package = "RGoogleDocs")
uploadDoc(f, auth, name = basename(f), binary = TRUE)
</r:code>
When <r:arg>binary</r:arg> is <r:true/>,
the <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func> function
calls <r:func>readBinary</r:func> which
amounts to calling
<r:expr>readBin(f, "raw", 22016)</r:expr>
as it determines the number of bytes in the file for us.
You can work with raw content yourself directly and upload that.
This is like uploading the contents as text when there is 
no associated file but the content was generated from a previous call.
For example, let's read the binary file ourselves:
<r:code>
vec = readBinary(f)
class(vec)
</r:code>
Then we can upload it, but again we have to specify the 
type and any name we want.
<r:code>
uploadDoc(vec, auth, type = "xls")
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
You can also upload material to a specific folder.
We do this by specifying the identity of the folder
via <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func>'s  <r:arg>folder</r:arg> parameter.
This should be a <r:class>GoogleFolder</r:class> object
retrieved from, for example, a call to <r:func>getDocs</r:func>
or <r:func>listFolder</r:func>.
We get the list of "documents"
<r:code>
  docs = getDocs(con)
</r:code>
and then can upload a file to say "MyFolder" using
<r:code>
  uploadDoc(x, con, name = "boo", type = "csv", folder = docs$MyFolder)
</r:code>
A more convenient version of this is
<r:code>
  f[["boo1", type = 'csv']] = x
</r:code>
where we "assign" the value to a name within the folder as if it were a list.
Note that we can specify the type and other arguments that are passed
on to <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func>.
Also note that the connection object is obtained from the folder object.
</para>
<para>
We can also specify the folder by name, e.g.,
<r:code>
  uploadDoc(x, con, name = "boo2", type = "csv", folder = "MyFolder")
</r:code>
But be aware that this involves an implicit call to <r:func>getDocs</r:func>
and so involves an extra "trip to the server".
</para>
<para>
Finally, if you happen to know the "internal" identity of the folder,
i.e. is /feeds/folders/.../ URL, you can specify this.
But note that it must be "escaped" using the <r:func>I</r:func>
function, e.g.,
<r:code>
  uploadDoc(x, con, name = "boo3", type = "csv", folder = I(docs$MyFolder@content["src"]))
</r:code>
</para>
<section>
<title>Tools for working with word processing documents</title>
<para>
The word processing documents are just HTML documents.  So we can use
<r:func>htmlParse</r:func> (or <r:func>htmlTreeParse</r:func>) and the
XPath to find what we want.  We can get the content or find the nodes
of interest and modify them and then upload the resulting document.
We have provided some simple functions for accessing elements of a
word processing document.  These are <r:func>comments</r:func>,
<r:func>images</r:func>, <r:func>footnotes</r:func> and
<r:func>sections</r:func>.  Each of these takes either the name of a
document and a connection (returned from
<r:func>getConnection</r:func>) or the parsed HTML document.
For example, we can call each of these as either:
<r:code>
comments("Many Parts", con)
doc = htmlParse(getDocContent("Many Parts", con), asText = TRUE, error = function(...) {})
comments(doc)
sections(doc)
</r:code>
The latter approach avoids retrieving the document and parsing it multiple
times.
</para>
<para>
<r:func>comments</r:func> returns a data frame with a row
for each comment and columns giving
the text of the comment, the date the comment was last
modified ( or created?) and the name of the author of the comment.
</para>
<para>
<r:func>sections</r:func> returns a character vector giving the
title of the different sections. The names of the elements
of this vector are numbers giving the level of the section.
This is taken from the h1, h2, h3, ..., h6 elements in the HTML document.
</para>
<para>
The <r:func>footnotes</r:func> function returns
a character vector giving the text of the footnotes.
The names are the unique identifiers within the document of these elements.
</para>
<para>
<r:func>images</r:func> returns the names of the image files referenced
within the document.  Note  that these are not the original names of the
image files, but the names as they are stored within the Google documents repository.
</para>
</section>


<section>
<title>Spreadsheets</title>
<para>
We have added basic functions for working with spreadsheets.
We create a connection for working with spreadsheets rather than word processing
documents. We do this by specifying the service as "wise" rather than
the default "writely".
<r:code>
  sheets.con = getGoogleDocsConnection(getGoogleAuth("dtemplelang@gmail.com", "...", service = "wise"))
</r:code>
When we call <r:func>getDocs</r:func> with this connection, we get back
information about spreadsheets only.
<r:code>
  a = getDocs(sheets.con)
</r:code>
The function <r:func>getWorksheets</r:func> is used
to obtain a list of objects that identify each of the worksheets within
a spreadsheet.
<r:code>
  ts = getWorksheets(a$TwoSheets, sheets.con)
  names(ts)
</r:code>
<r:func>getWorksheets</r:func> is smart enough to  be able to
work from the name of the spreadsheet, e.g.
<r:code>
  ts = getWorksheets("TwoSheets", sheets.con)
</r:code>
but it is faster to use the GoogleDocument object returned via
<r:func>getDocs</r:func> as it avoids an extra request to the
Google Docs server.
</para>

<para>
We can do various things with the spreadsheet and its worksheets.
We can query the dimensions and/or the contents of the worksheet or a part of it,
we can modify one or more cells, and we can add a worksheet to a spreadsheet.
The functions <r:func>dim</r:func>, <r:func>nrow</r:func> and
<r:func>ncol</r:func> all work.
These report the "declared" dimensions of the worksheet,
i.e. how many rows and columns have been allocated.
This is often way more than are actually used.
The function <r:func>getExtent</r:func> tells us
about the rectangular region that is actually in use.
This returns a 2 x 2 matrix giving the "bounding box"
of the effective cells in use.
If there is nothing in the first row and column,
this would return 2, 2 as the indices of the
first cell. 
</para>
<para>
We can convert a worksheet to a matrix or data frame using 
the regular <r:func>as</r:func> function, e.g.
<r:expr>as(sheet, "matrix")</r:expr>
or
<r:expr>as(sheet, "data.frame")</r:expr>.
The coercion methods are merely calls to
the function <r:func>sheetAsMatrix</r:func>
which provides more control of the coercion.
It allows us to specify how the column names
are found (e.g. as the first row of the worksheet,
or given in the call as the value of the <r:arg>header</r:arg> parameter)
and whether to discard "empty" rows and columns.
For example, 
<r:code>
  sheetAsMatrix(ts$Sheet1, header = TRUE, as.data.frame = TRUE, trim = TRUE)
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
If we want to access one or more cells, we can convert the entire
worksheet into a data frame and then use R's regular subsetting.
However, this is potentially expensive in that we have to download the
entire worksheet and then process all of the contents.  If the
worksheet is large and we only want a few values, we are doing a lot
of extra work.  
So we have provided methods for the subsetting operator <r:op>[</r:op>
that do this more efficiently by retrieving and processing only the
specified cells.
We can use these on the <r:class>GoogleWorksheetRef</r:class> objects.
For example, suppose we have our sheet with 
<r:code>
con = getGoogleDocsConnection("me", "my password")
mine4 = getWorksheets("mine4", con)[[1]]
</r:code>
then we can get a single cell with
<r:code>
mine4[2, 3]
</r:code>
We can get multiple cell values, e.g.
<r:code>
mine4[1:2, ]
mine4[, 2:3]
mine4[1, ]
mine4[, 3]
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
We can also assign values to one or more cells.
Let's start by adding a new worksheet to the spreadsheet mine4:
<r:code>
mine4 = getDocs(con)$mine4
sh = addWorksheet(mine4, con, "test")
</r:code>
Now we can populate it
<r:code>
sh[1,1] = 2
sh[2, 1:10] = letters[1:10]
sh[, 11] = letters[1:5]
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
When we omit a dimension, the affected cells
range over the extent
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adding Documents</title>
<para>
We can use <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func> to upload 
a document or even an R object such as a data frame or matrix
which will be converted to a spreadsheet via a CSV upload.
We can use <r:func>addSpreadsheet</r:func> to create a spreadsheet
document with a single empty worksheet of specified dimensions.
This is a simple wrapper for <r:func>uploadDoc</r:func>
Note that when uploading a document using either of these
functions, you are communicating with the documents API,
i.e. writely, and you need authentication for that.
So if you have a connection for the spreadsheets API, you cannot
use that.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Managing Documents</title>
<para>
We have been focusing on the contents of documents.
The Google Docs API allows us to manage the collection of documents.
It provides functionality to upload and delete/remove documents,
rename documents, create folders and move documents into folders.


The function <r:func>addFolder</r:func> allows us to create
a new folder. This is created at the top-level.
We can then move it to a different folder.
The function <r:func>moveToFolder</r:func> does this.
<r:func>addFolder</r:func> takes one or more  names
and a connection and creates the folders with these names.
<r:code>
f = addFolder(c("foo", "bar"), con)
</r:code>
The results are <r:class>GoogleFolder</r:class> objects.
We can use these as target/destinations  in
calls to <r:func>moveToFolder</r:func>.
For example, we can move the folder bar into foo with
<r:code>
moveToFolder(f$bar, f$foo)
</r:code>
</para>
<para>
We can change meta data, such as the title, of the document.
This is done via the operators <r:op>$*&lt;-</r:op> and <r:op>[&lt;-</r:op>.
(The accessor methods are not supported.)
Given a document <r:var>doc</r:var> we set, e.g., the title with
<r:code>
doc$title = "new title"
</r:code>
We can also use 
<r:code>
doc["title"] = "new title"
</r:code>
The benefit of the second approach (apart from allowing variables, 
e.g. <r:expr>var = "title"; doc[ var ] = value</r:expr>)
is that we can set multiple values in a single call, e.g.
<r:code>
doc["title", "author"] = list("new title", c(name = "Bob", email = "bob@bob.com"))
</r:code>
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Comment</title>
<para>
The Google documents and spreadsheets servics are interesting. The
Web-based nature has several attractive aspects. However, the
interactive tools are currently quite limited relative to regular
office applications.  There is little functionality for working richly
with styles.  The APIs are also reasonably limited.  Furthermore, some
of the documentation is slightly unclear and even incorrect, e.g. the
code for some examples do not correspond to what is being discussed in
the text, the batch editing section talks about POST, but in fact PUT
works and POST does not appear to.  While developing some of the
functionality in this package, the Google service claimed it was
experiencing technical difficulties and was unable to list all my
documents.
So I am not ready to trade-in my office tools (not that I use them
very much anyway!), but the notion of publishing "live" documents is
appealing.  The IDynDocs package has a different take on "live".
</para>
</section>
</article>
